A Finding Aid to the Robert Ebendorf Papers, 1920-2015, bulk 1960-2010, in the Archives of American Art AAA.ebenrobe
Archives of American Art
Robert Ebendorf papers
bulk 1960-2010
1920-2015
AAA.ebenrobe
Archives of American Art
4.8 Linear feet
The papers of metalsmith and jeweler Robert Ebendorf measure 4.8 linear feet and date from 1920 to 2015, with the bulk of the material from 1960 to 2010. The papers document Ebendorf’s career through scattered biographical material; business correspondence with galleries, universities, and professional groups as well as personal correspondence with friends and family, including a large collection of mail art; artist statements, teaching philosophies, and reflections by Ebendorf as well as writings by others; application materials for the artist’s position as Belk Chair at East Carolina University, student fellowship applications, and other teaching files; inventories, invoices, and publicity material, including several folders of notes and materials for retrospectives; exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and other printed material; sketches, cut paper, and collage work loose and in sketchbooks; and photographic materials of the artist, friends, family, and artwork.
Ebendorf, Robert, 1938-
Biographical/Historical note
Robert Ebendorf (1938-) is a metalsmith and jeweler in Greenville, North Carolina. Ebendorf was born in Topeka, Kansas, and earned a BFA in 1958 and an MFA in 1963 from the University of Kansas. Upon receiving a Fulbright grant, he studied in Norway at the School for Applied Arts and Crafts in 1963 and returned to work at Norway Silver Designs in Fredikstad on a Louis Comfort Tiffany Foundation grant from 1965 to 1966.
A founding member and once president of the Society of North American Goldsmiths, Ebendorf has been deeply committed to forwarding the metals field as an innovator, organizer, and teacher. The artist is known for his original combinations of precious and non-precious materials alongside found objects and has held teaching positions at Stetson University, the State University of New York at New Paltz, Haystack Mountain School of Crafts in Maine, Penland School of Crafts in North Carolina, and East Carolina University.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of metalsmith and jeweler Robert Ebendorf measure 4.8 linear feet and date from 1920 to 2015, with the bulk of the material from 1960 to 2010. The papers document Ebendorf’s career through scattered biographical material; business correspondence with galleries, universities, and professional groups as well as personal correspondence with friends and family, including a large collection of mail art; artist statements, teaching philosophies, and reflections by Ebendorf as well as writings by others; application materials for the artist’s position as Belk Chair at East Carolina University, student fellowship applications, and other teaching files; inventories, invoices, and publicity material, including several folders of notes and materials for retrospectives; exhibition catalogs, news clippings, and other printed material; sketches, cut paper, and collage work loose and in sketchbooks; and photographic materials of the artist, friends, family, and artwork.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated by Robert Ebendorf in 2015.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Use of sound recordings requires advance notice. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as nine series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1920-2014 (Boxes 1, 6; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1965-2015 (Boxes 1-2; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1945-2014 (Box 2; 4 folders)
Series 4: Teaching Files, 1974-2012 (Box 2; 5 folders)
Series 5: Personal Business Records, circa 1963-2006 (Box 2; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 6: Printed Material, 1949-2015 (Boxes 2-3, 6; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 7: Artwork, circa 1940-1987 (Boxes 3, 6; 0.2 linear feet)
Series 8: Sketchbooks, circa 1963-1968 (Boxes 3, 6; 5 folders)
Series 9: Photographs, circa 1920-2012 (Boxes 3-7; 1.9 linear feet)
Related Archival Materials note
Also in the Archives of American Art is an oral history interview of Robert Ebendorf conducted 2004 April 16-18, by Tacey Rosolowski, in Greenville, N.C.
East Carolina University. -- Faculty; Art--Study and teaching; Collages; Jewelers--North Carolina; Mail art; Metal-workers--North Carolina; Sketchbooks; Sketches
- Biographical Material, 1920-2014; Series 1; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 1, 6
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes academic transcripts from the University of Kansas; professional and personal awards and certificates; a curriculum vitae circa 2010; lifetime achievement awards and applications; family files; a purchased love letter written to a black soldier in 1920; an interview on 1 CD with Lake Effect's Bonnie North on NPR Milwaukee from August 5, 2014; pins and conference nametags; and a citizen commendation from the New York City Police Department. Miscellaneous biographical material consists of a business card, high school graduation program, letter to parents from the Kansas Governor for their 50th wedding anniversary, workshop flyer with brief bio, wedding announcement with Aleta Braun, and photocopies of portrait illustrations by Jess Taylor.
  - Academic Transcripts, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards and Certificates, 1954-2014 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 2010 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - ECU Lifetime Achievement Award, Letters of Recommendation, 2003-2014 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Family, Herb Ebendorf, 1982-2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Family, Sue Springer, 1963-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gardner Award Application, 2010; 1 Sound discs (CD) (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Oversized printed application template housed in Box 6, Folder 1.
  - Gardner Award, Letters of Recommendation, 2010 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Love Letter (Purchased), 1920 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Biographical Material, 1954-2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - NPR Interview with Bonnie North, 2014; 1 Sound discs (CD) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pin and Nametags, 2004, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gardner Application and Police Department Commendation, 1979-2010 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1965-2015; Series 2; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Correspondence is chiefly collaged, drawn, and stitched mail art with wife Aleta Braun, a colleague’s son Louis Bailey, students, and friends. There is also business correspondence with museums, universities, and professional societies regarding commissions, exhibitions, and academic positions; correspondence with Emprise Financial in Kansas; and personal correspondence with friends, family, and colleagues.
  - Business Correspondence, 1965-2013 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence with Emprise Financial, 2006-2010 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mail Art, Aleta Braun, 1997-2015 (Box 1, Folder 16-18)
  - Mail Art, Louis Bailey, 2000-2003 (Box 1, Folder 19-25)
  - Mail Art, Miscellaneous, 2000-2014 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1978-2015 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Writings, circa 1945-2014; Series 3; 4 Folders Box 2
  Writings by Robert Ebendorf include artist statements, short autobiographies, teaching philosophies, reflections, and exhibition statements, while writings about Ebendorf include essays, reports, speeches, and a manuscript of Robert W. Ebendorf: The Work in Depth published by the Racine Art Museum. Also found in this series are a poem and short essay by Elliot Smith; a biography sent by the artist’s uncle Herb mentioning Ebendorf’s great-grandfather circa 1945; a short story by daughter Brittany; and an application essay by wife Aleta Braun for the Jentel Artist Residency in Wyoming.
  - Writings by Robert Ebendorf, circa 1988-2013 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Writings About Robert Ebendorf, circa 1975-2014 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Writings by Elliot Smith, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Writings by Family, circa 1945-2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Teaching Files, 1974-2012; Series 4; 5 Folders Box 2
  This series consists of application materials for the Belk Distinguished Chair position at East Carolina University, student applications and letters of recommendation for various fellowship programs, and miscellaneous teaching files, including student project proposals, certificates of teacher-student impact from ECU, research notes, and a list of international museums and galleries, possibly for Fulbright study.
  - ECU Application, Belk Chair, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - ECU Application, Letters of Recommendation, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Teaching Files, 1984-2012 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Student Applications and Letters of Recommendation, 1974-2003 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1963-2006; Series 5; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2
  Personal business records include images, correspondence, and publicity material for the Formica design award won by Ebendorf and then-wife Ivy Ross in 1984. Files on retrospective exhibitions includes images of and notes on material to be included, checklists of artwork, exhibition writings, loan receipts, and correspondence. Also found in this series are inventories of artwork, a mailing list of individuals and museums, and records of financial and material exchanges with museums.
  - Formica Corporation, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Inventories, 1978-2006 (Box 2, Folder 15-19)
  - Mailing List, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Museum Invoices, Receipts, and Loan Records, 1978-2003 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Retrospective at NC State, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Retrospective at New Paltz, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Retrospective at New Paltz, Material and Notes, circa 1963-1989 (Box 2, Folder 24-30)
- Printed Material, 1949-2015; Series 6; 0.7 Linear feet Boxes 2-3, 6
  This series contains magazines, bulletins, and news clippings regarding Ebendorf and his artwork as well as exhibition announcements, brochures, catalogs, and signage.
  - Exhibition Announcements and Brochures, 1965-2015 (Box 2, Folder 31-34)
    Oversized exhibition poster housed in Box 6, Folder 2.
  - Exhibition Announcements and Brochures, 1989-2015 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1980-2008 (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    Oversized exhibition catalog housed in Box 6, Folder 2.
  - Exhibition Signage, circa 2013 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Magazines and Bulletins, 1973-2014 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Oversized Florida Craftsmen bulletin housed in Box 6, Folder 2.
  - News Clippings, 1949-2014 (Box 3, Folder 6-17)
    Oversized news clippings housed in Box 6, Folder 2.
  - Oversized Exhibition Posters & Catalogs, News Clippings, and Bulletin, circa 1968-2006 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Artwork, circa 1940s-1987; Series 7; 0.2 Linear feet Boxes 3, 6
  This series contains artwork from Ebendorf’s childhood in the 1940s, a collaged book titled “The Pilgrim of Love,” cut-paper designs on cardstock, scans of sketches and sketchbook pages, as well as a number of loose sketches and drawings, including a set from Ebendorf’s freshman class, Nature Drawing I, at the University of Kansas in 1956.
  - Childhood Artwork, circa 1940 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Collage Book, "The Pilgrim of Love", undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Cut-Paper Work, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Scanned Sketches, circa 1963-1987 (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
  - Sketches, undated (Box 3, Folder 23-25)
    Oversized loose sketches housed in Box 6, Folder 3.
  - Drawings and Loose Sketches, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Nature Drawing I, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Sketchbooks, 1963-1966, undated; Series 8; 5 Folders Boxes 3, 6
  Most of the sketchbooks included are from Ebendorf’s time in Norway with a Fulbright Fellowship from 1963 to 1964 and a Tiffany Foundation Grant from 1965 to 1966. An additional sketchbook includes images of designs for a medal commissioned by the Medical College of Georgia.
  - Medical College of Georgia Commission, circa 1968 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Norway Tiffany, Small, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Norway Fulbright: Norwegian Folk Museum, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Norway Fulbright: Norwegian Folk Museum and Natural History Museum, 1963-1964 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Norway Tiffany, Large, 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Photographs, circa 1920-2012; Series 9; 1.9 Linear feet Boxes 3-7
  This series includes formal and informal images of the artist with works, in his studio, and teaching students. There are also photographs, negatives, and an annotated album of family, friends, and colleagues as well as color transparencies of the house Ebendorf shared with first wife Sue Springer in New Paltz in the early 1980s. Images of exhibitions and artwork include photographs, negatives, color transparencies, an extensive collection of 35-mm slides, and digital prints. An oversized portrait photograph of Ebendorf is housed in OV 7.
  - Robert Ebendorf, 1938-2012 (Box 3, Folder 28-33)
    Oversized photographs of Robert Ebendorf housed in Box 6, Folder 8, and OV 7.
  - Ebendorf Family, Photographs and Slides, circa 1920-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Family, Friends, and Colleagues, 1965-2007 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Family, Friends, and Colleagues, Album, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Family, Friends, and Colleagues, Negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - House at New Paltz, Color Transparencies, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Exhibitions, circa 1960-2005 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Artwork, circa 1950-2010 (Box 4, Folder 7-20)
    Oversized photographs of artwork housed in Box 6, Folder 8.
  - Artwork, Color Transparencies, 1938-1985, undated (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
  - Artwork, Negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Artwork, Slides, 1965-2002 (Box 4, Folder 24-32)
  - Artwork, Slides, 1980-2004 (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
  - Artwork, Digital Prints, circa 2000-2010 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
  - Oversized Photographs of Robert Ebendorf and Artwork, circa 1965-2005 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Photograph of Robert Ebendorf, circa 2000 (Box OV 7)